Preliminary Guide to the A. Hollis Edens Records,1949 - 1960
Duke University. University Archives
A. Hollis Edens records 1949 - 1960
Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-
52 linear feet Extent: 52,000 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Arthur Hollis Edens (1901-1968) had a long career as an educator and administrator. He served as president of Duke University from 1949 to 1960. During that time, Edens focused on fund-raising and long range planning, and oversaw the implementation of a new student union and a University Council for faculty members. The A. Hollis Edens records include correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, and other documents related to Edens's career at Duke. Among the major subjects of the collection focused on Duke University are its administration and development, the Board of Trustees, the Duke Endowment, Annual Reports from major divisions of the university, segregation, and Edens's inauguration in 1949. Prominent people in the collection include faculty member Paul M. Gross and presidential assistant Earl W. Potter. The collection also includes documents related to Edens's membership in organizations such as the U.S. State Department's Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange, the National Commission on Accrediting, the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, the Southern University Conference, the Methodist Church, and the President's Committee on Education Beyond the High School. English.
UA.03.57.0001
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the President and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The A. Hollis Edens Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1964 (A64-50), 1974 (A74-198), 1989 (A89-95), 1993 (A93-74).
Biographical Note
Arthur Hollis Edens was born on February 14, 1901, in Willow Grove, Tennessee. He was the son of Everett C. Edens, a Methodist minister, and Barbara Ellen (Jolly) Edens. He attended Emory University, from which he received the degrees of B.Ph. (1930) and M.A. (1938). He also received a Master of Public Administration degree (1944) and a Ph.D. (1949) from Harvard University. Prior to coming to Duke, Edens worked as a teacher and administrator at the Cumberland Mountain School and Emory University. In 1946, he was named Dean of Administration at Emory, and in 1947 became Vice Chancellor of the University System of Georgia. In 1948, he was appointed associate director of the General Education Board of the Rockefeller Foundation.
In November 1948, the trustees of Duke University selected Edens to serve as president of the institution. Edens began his presidency on March 15, 1949. With inflation rapidly eroding purchasing power, the University launched a capital gifts program and a national development campaign. Edens noted that upon entering the field of fund raising Duke faced a "peculiar handicap." He stated, "Never before had we sought sizeable sums from either alumni or the general public. Indeed, the magnitude of James B. Duke's Indenture had been such as to encourage the uninformed public to believe that Duke University never would require additional capital." Through the success of this campaign Duke University began to build its own endowment and expand its programs. Academic units such as the Center for Commonwealth Studies and the Center for the Study of Aging date from this time. Formal participation of the faculty in governance began in 1952 with the formation of a University Council and the consolidation of several committees into an Undergraduate Faculty Council. Additional accomplishments included the establishment of the James B. Duke Endowed Professorships, the organization of a student union program (the Duke University Union) to enhance student life, and a vigorous defense of academic freedom during the McCarthy Era. Though not so well known because he chose to work behind the scenes, Edens also assiduously sought to have the segregated admissions policy of the University changed.
Following disagreements with the Board of Trustees and some members of the faculty, Edens resigned on February 19, 1960. After leaving Duke, Edens served for five years as executive director of the Mary Reynolds Babcock Foundation in Winston-Salem, N.C. Edens died in Atlanta, Georgia, on August 7, 1968. He was survived by his wife, Mary Kathleen (Russell) Edens, and his daughter, Mrs. Jefferson D. Wingfield, Jr.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, conference materials, and other documents related to Edens's professional career. The collection is divided into eight series. The first and largest series,Subject Files, is arranged alphabetically by topic, and chronologically within each subject. Correspondence is filed by name of correspondent; miscellaneous correspondence is filed alphabetically at the beginning of each letter group. The next series,U. S. State Department's Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange, contains papers from Edens's service on this commission. The third series,National Commission on Accrediting, contains papers from Edens's service on this commission.Inauguration, the fourth series, includes material on Edens's presidential inauguration in 1949. The next series,Annual Reports to the President, contains the reports submitted to the president by major divisions of the university. The sixth series,Assistant to the President, Earl W. Porter (1956-1960), contains the papers of Edens's assistant. The seventh series,Segregation Policy Petitions, involves the desegregation process at Duke University. The next series,U.S. State Department, International Educational Exchange Service, details Edens's involvement with that organization. The ninth series,Gross-Edens Controversy, consists of papers relating to Edens's resignation. This series is restricted. The final series is Oversized Materials and includes items from Edens's inauguration as president of Duke.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Duke University -- Endowments; Duke University. President; Duke University -- Presidents; Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986; Methodist Church -- North Carolina; National Commission on Accrediting; Segregation in higher education; Southern Association of Colleges and Schools; Southern University Conference; United States. Advisory Commission on Educational Exchange; United States. Advisory Committee on Education; Universities and colleges -- Inaugural ceremonies
Contents of Collection
- Subject Files
  - Correspondence
    - Aa-An (Box 1)
    - Ao-Az (Box 1)
  - Allen, George Garland (Box 1)
  - American Academy in Rome (Box 1)
  - American Assembly (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors (Box 1)
  - American Cancer Society (Box 1)
  - American Chemical Society (Box 1)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (Box 1)
  - American Committee for Emigre Scholars, Writers, and Artists (Box 1)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education, [4 folders] (Box 2)
  - American Council on Education (Box 2)
    - [Hobbs] (Box 2)
    - Committee on Character Development, [2 folders] (Box 2)
    - Committee on Taxation and Fiscal Reporting (Box 3)
    - Minutes, [4 folders] (Box 3)
  - American Institute of Management (Box 3)
  - AMERICAN LITERATURE (Box 3)
  - American Political Science Association (Box 3)
  - American Psychological Association (Box 3)
  - American Society for International Law (Box 3)
  - American Society for Public Administration (Box 3)
  - American Universities Field Staff (Box 3)
  - Archie, W. C. (Box 3)
  - Army Research Office -- Durham, [2 folders] (Box 4)
  - Asbury United Methodist Church, Durham, NC (Box 4)
  - Asia Foundation (Box 4)
  - Association for Higher Education (Box 4)
  - Association of American Colleges, [2 folders] (Box 4)
  - Association of American Law Schools (Box 4)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges (Box 4)
  - Association of American Universities, [3 folders] (Box 4)
  - Association of American Universities (Box 5)
  - Association of American Universities (Box 5)
    - Annual Meeting,1958, [2 folders] (Box 5)
    - Committee on Accrediting, [2 folders] (Box 5)
    - Committee on Outside Activities of Faculty (Box 5)
    - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Minutes (Box 5)
    - Reports, [2 folders] (Box 6)
    - "The Rights and Responsibilities of Universities & Their Faculties" (Box 6)
  - Association of Universities of the British Commonwealth (Box 6)
  - Associations -- Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Atlantic Coast Conference (Box 6)
  - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Baa-Bar (Box 6)
    - Bas-Bep (Box 6)
    - Ber-Bn (Box 7)
    - Bo-Bp (Box 7)
    - Bra-Broo (Box 7)
    - Brown-Bs (Box 7)
    - Bt-Bz (Box 7)
  - Bahia University -- Salvador, Brazil (Box 7)
  - Bell, William Brown -- Estate (Box 7)
  - Board of Control for Southern Regional Education (Box 7)
  - Board of Control for Southern Regional Education (Box 8)
  - Boy Scouts of America (Box 8)
  - Brookings-Duke Conference on International Relations (Box 8)
  - Brower, A. S., [2 folders] (Box 8)
  - Bryson, E. C. (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - Caa-Carp (Box 8)
    - Carr-Cher (Box 8)
    - Ches-Cl (Box 9)
    - Coa-Con (Box 9)
    - Coo-Cra (Box 9)
    - Cre-Cz (Box 9)
  - Calkins, Robert D. (Box 9)
  - Campbell, John Bulow, Foundation (Box 9)
  - Cannon, Charles A. (Box 9)
  - Carnegie Corporation (Box 9)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace (Box 9)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching (Box 9)
  - Century Association (Box 9)
  - Chapel Hill, N.C. -- Ordinances (Box 10)
  - Charlotte High School, Charlotte, NC (Box 10)
  - Chicago University, Chicago, Il (Box 10)
  - China Medical Board, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Cleland, James Tough (Box 10)
  - Clippings (Box 10)
  - Clyde, Paul Hibbert (Box 10)
  - Cocke, Norman A. (Box 10)
  - Faculty Petition to the Board of Trustees,March 1962 (Box 10)
  - College Celebrations (Box 10)
  - College Entrance Examination Board (Box 10)
  - College Life Insurance Company of America (Box 10)
  - Colwell, Ernest Cadman (Box 10)
  - Communism (Box 10)
  - Conferences [Miscellaneous] (Box 10)
  - Connery, Robert (Box 10)
  - Cooperative Research Foundation (Box 10)
  - Council for Financial Aid to Education, Inc. (Box 10)
  - Council of Church-Related Colleges of North Carolina (Box 10)
  - Council of Southern Universities -- Southern Fellowship Fund (Box 10)
  - Council of Southern Universities -- Southern Fellowship Fund, [3 folders] (Box 11)
  - Council on Confederation in Teacher Education (Box 11)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 11)
  - Council on Library Resources (Box 11)
  - Council on Student Travel (Box 11)
  - Crank Letters, [2 folders] (Box 11)
  - Cresap, McCormick and Paget (Box 11)
  - Correspondence (Box 11)
    - Da-Dd (Box 12)
    - De-Dj (Box 12)
    - Dk-Dul (Box 12)
    - Dum-Dz (Box 12)
  - Damon Runyan Memorial Fund for Cancer Research (Box 12)
  - Danforth Foundation (Box 12)
  - Dicks, Russell (Box 12)
  - Dort, Wakefield, Jr. (Box 12)
  - Dozier, John M. (Box 12)
  - Duke, Doris (Box 12)
  - Duke Endowment (Box 12)
  - Duke Endowment (Box 12)
    - Investments (Box 12)
    - Rural Church Section (Box 12)
    - Superannuate Fund,1949-1957, [8 folders] (Box 13)
    - Superannuate Fund,1959 (Box 14)
  - DUKE MATHEMATICAL JOURNAL (Box 14)
  - Duke Memorial United Methodist Church, Durham, NC (Box 14)
  - Duke University (Box 14)
    - Academic Honor System (Box 14)
    - Addressograph Office (Box 14)
    - Administrative Committee, [2 folders] (Box 14)
    - Administrative Study Committee (Box 14)
    - Admissions (Box 14)
    - Admissions Committee (Box 14)
    - Admissions Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Aesthetics, Art, and Music Department, [2 folders] (Box 15)
    - Aims (Box 15)
    - Air Force ROTC, [3 folders] (Box 15)
    - Allen Building (Box 15)
    - Alumni Affairs Department, [2 folders] (Box 15)
    - Angier B. Duke Scholarships (Box 16)
    - Applications for Employment (Box 16)
    - Archives Committee (Box 16)
    - Army ROTC (Box 16)
    - Artists Series (Box 16)
    - Arts Center (Box 16)
    - Association Memberships (Box 16)
    - Athletic Council (Box 16)
    - Athletic Department (Box 16)
    - Athletics [Football] (Box 16)
    - Baldwin Scholarship Fund (Box 16)
    - Band (Box 16)
    - Board of Trustees (Box 16)
      - Building Committee (Box 16)
      - Bylaws Committee (Box 16)
      - Law School Committee (Box 16)
    - Botany Department, [2 folders] (Box 16)
    - Brown Folklore Collection (Box 16)
    - Budget (Box 16)
    - Buildings, Naming of (Box 16)
    - BULLETIN (Box 16)
    - Bureau of Public Information (Box 16)
    - Bureau of Testing and Guidance (Box 16)
    - Bus Service Between Campuses (Box 16)
    - Business Office. Non-Academic Employees [Retired] (Box 16)
    - Calendar (Box 17)
    - Campus Chest (Box 17)
    - Centennial of Teacher Education (Box 17)
    - Center for the Study of Aging (Box 17)
    - Central Records Office (Box 17)
    - Chapel (Box 17)
    - Chapel Administrative Committee (Box 17)
    - Chapel Organ (Box 17)
    - Duke University Chemistry Department, [2 folders] (Box 17)
    - Duke University CHRONICLE (Box 17)
    - College Public Lectures Committee (Box 17)
    - Commencement, [3 folders] (Box 17)
    - Commencement (Box 18)
    - Commencement Marshals, [2 folders] (Box 18)
    - Committees (Box 18)
    - Commonwealth Studies Center (Box 18)
    - Contracts (Box 18)
    - Courses of Instruction Committee (Box 18)
    - Curriculum Committee (Box 18)
    - Dads' Day (Box 18)
    - Debate (Box 18)
    - Defense Activities (Box 18)
    - Degree Statistics (Box 18)
    - Denominational Centers (Box 18)
    - Development Campaign, [9 folders] (Box 19)
    - Development Office (Box 19)
    - Development Program (Box 19)
    - Development Program, [2 folders] (Box 20)
    - Divinity School, [3 folders] (Box 20)
    - Divinity School (Box 20)
      - Christian Convocation (Box 21)
      - Dean, [3 folders] (Box 21)
      - Divinity School One Percent Plan (Box 21)
      - Petitions (Box 21)
      - Segregation Question (Box 21)
    - Economics and Business Administration Department, [2 folders] (Box 21)
    - Education Department, [2 folders] (Box 21)
    - Education Department (Box 22)
    - Educational Facilities Committee (Box 22)
    - Engineering Council (Box 22)
    - Engineering School, [3 folders] (Box 22)
    - English Department, [2 folders] (Box 22)
    - English Usage Committee (Box 22)
    - Enrollment Statistics (Box 22)
    - Examinations (Box 22)
    - Faculty (Box 23)
      - [Retired and Deceased] (Box 23)
      - Benefits (Box 23)
      - Benefits [Social Security] (Box 23)
      - Benefits [Tuition Awards] (Box 23)
      - Club (Box 23)
      - Council (Box 23)
      - Data (Box 23)
      - Health Insurance (Box 23)
      - Housing (Box 23)
      - Letters (Box 23)
      - Reorganization Commission, [2 folders] (Box 23)
      - Retirements (Box 23)
      - Salaries (Box 23)
      - Salary Letters (Box 23)
    - Financial Aid Committee (Box 24)
    - Financial Data (Box 24)
    - Flag Raising (Box 24)
    - Foreign Students, Study, etc. (Box 24)
    - Foreign Visitors, [2 folders] (Box 24)
    - Forestry School (Box 24)
    - Founders' Day, [2 folders] (Box 24)
    - Freshman Class (Box 24)
    - Freshman Handbook (Box 24)
    - Geology Department (Box 24)
    - German Department (Box 24)
    - Gerontology Council (Box 24)
    - Golf Course (Box 25)
    - Graduate Council (Box 25)
    - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences (Box 25)
    - Grants and Gifts (Box 25)
    - Greek Department (Box 25)
    - Hanes House (Box 25)
    - History Department, [2 folders] (Box 25)
    - Honor System Committee (Box 25)
    - Honorary Degrees (Box 25)
    - James B. Duke Professorships (Box 25)
    - Latin Department (Box 25)
    - Law School (Box 25)
    - Law School, [3 folders] (Box 26)
    - Law School Dean, [3 folders] (Box 26)
    - Law School World Rule of Law Center (Box 26)
    - Library, [2 folders] (Box 27)
    - Library Flowers Collection, [2 folders] (Box 27)
    - Library Cooperative Project (Box 27)
    - Library Council (Box 27)
    - Loan Funds (Box 27)
    - Loyalty Fund, [2 folders] (Box 27)
    - Marine Laboratory, [2 folders] (Box 27)
    - Mathematics Department (Box 27)
    - Medical Center, [2 folders] (Box 27)
    - Medical Center Hospital, [3 folders] (Box 28)
    - Medical Center Hospital School, [3 folders] (Box 28)
    - Medical Center Study (Box 28)
    - Men's Student Government Association (Box 28)
    - Methodist Student Center (Box 28)
    - Music Director (Box 28)
    - Naval ROTC (Box 28)
    - Naval ROTC (Box 29)
    - Negro Students (Box 29)
    - Non-Alumni Parents Committee (Box 29)
    - Nursing School, [3 folders] (Box 29)
    - Ordnance Institute of Chemical Physics (Box 29)
    - Page Auditorium (Box 29)
    - Parapsychology Laboratory (Box 29)
    - Parapsychology Laboratory (Box 30)
    - Parking and Traffic (Box 30)
    - Pastors' School (Box 30)
    - Peat, Marwick, Mitchell & Co. Scholarship in Public Accounting (Box 30)
    - Personnel Department (Box 30)
    - Philosophy Department, [2 folders] (Box 30)
    - Physical Education Department (Box 30)
    - Physical Education for Women (Box 30)
    - Physics Department, [2 folders] (Box 30)
    - Political Science Department, [2 folders] (Box 30)
    - Portraits Committee (Box 30)
    - President's Report (Box 30)
    - President's Report to the Board of Trustees (Box 30)
    - President's Report to the Faculty (Box 31)
    - Psychology Department, [2 folders] (Box 31)
    - Public Education Committee (Box 31)
    - Publications Board (Box 31)
    - Radio Station (Box 31)
    - Red Friars (Box 31)
    - Religion Department (Box 31)
    - Religious Council (Box 31)
    - Religious Life (Box 31)
    - Research Council (Box 31)
    - Research Grants (Box 31)
    - Retirement Annuities Committee (Box 31)
    - Rhodes Scholarship Committee (Box 31)
    - Romance Languages Department, [2 folders] (Box 31)
    - Sabbatical leaves, [5 folders] (Box 32)
    - Sabbatical leaves (Box 33)
    - Schedule Committee (Box 33)
    - School Law Conference (Box 33)
    - Science Teachers Laboratory Conference (Box 33)
    - Segregation Policy, [2 folders] (Box 33)
    - Segregation Policy -- Petitions [Oversize Material] (Box 33)
    - Senior Class Gifts (Box 33)
    - Sociology Department (Box 33)
    - Song Book (Box 33)
    - Statistics, [2 folders] (Box 33)
    - Steering Board (Box 33)
    - Student Activities (Box 33)
    - Student Affairs (Box 33)
    - Student Counseling (Box 33)
    - Student Loan Policy Committee (Box 33)
    - Student Publications [DUKE 'N' DUCHESS] (Box 33)
    - Student Union (Box 33)
    - Summer Session, [2 folders] (Box 34)
    - Telephone Service Survey (Box 34)
    - Trinity College Historical Society (Box 34)
    - Undergraduate Faculty Council (Box 34)
    - Undergraduate Student Counseling on Military Service Committee (Box 34)
    - University Council, [3 folders] (Box 34)
    - University Council (Box 34)
      - Committee on Organization (Box 34)
      - Committees (Box 34)
      - Correspondence (Box 34)
      - Minutes and Summaries, [2 folders] (Box 35)
      - Organization and Membership (Box 35)
      - Reports, [2 folders] (Box 35)
    - University House [Four Acres] (Box 35)
    - University Senate (Box 35)
    - Veterans' Education (Box 35)
    - Woman's College (Box 35)
    - Woman's College, [2 folders] (Box 36)
    - Woman's College (Box 36)
      - Admissions (Box 36)
      - Director of Religious Life (Box 36)
      - Naming of (Box 36)
      - Twenty-Fifth Anniversary (Box 36)
    - Zoology Department, [2 folders] (Box 36)
  - Duke University Church, [2 folders] (Box 36)
  - Duke University Press (Box 36)
  - Dukes, Charles A. (Box 36)
  - Dukes, Charles A., [4 folders] (Box 37)
  - DuMont, R. E. (Box 37)
  - DuPont Seminars (Box 37)
  - Durham, NC (Box 37)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 37)
    - Citizen's Hospital Committee (Box 37)
    - Community Redevelopment Commission (Box 37)
    - Durham's Committee of 100 (Box 37)
    - Human Relations Committee (Box 37)
    - Railroad Station (Box 37)
    - Television Stations, [2 folders] (Box 38)
  - Durham Arts Council (Box 38)
  - Durham Cerebral Palsy Foundation (Box 38)
  - Durham Committee on Rural Churches (Box 38)
  - Durham Community Chest, Inc. (Box 38)
  - Correspondence (Box 38)
    - Ea-El (Box 38)
    - Em-Ez (Box 38)
  - Earle, Ralph (Box 38)
  - Edens, Arthur Hollis (Box 38)
    - Congratulatory Letters (Box 38)
    - Inauguration as President of Duke University [see also Boxes 82-85] (Box 38)
    - Invitations (Box 38)
    - Memoranda (Box 39)
    - Miscellany (Box 39)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight David (Box 39)
  - Emory University, Atlanta, GA (Box 39)
  - Emory University, Atlanta, GA -- Public Affairs Clinic (Box 39)
  - English-Speaking Union of the United States (Box 39)
  - Exchange Programs (Box 39)
  - Correspondence (Box 39)
    - Fa-Fik (Box 39)
    - Fil-Fo (Box 39)
    - Fp-Fz (Box 39)
  - Few, William Preston -- Memorial Volume (Box 39)
  - Financing Higher Education (Box 39)
  - Flowers, Robert Lee -- Will (Box 39)
  - Ford Foundation, [1 folders] (Box 39)
  - Ford Foundation, [2 folders] (Box 40)
  - Ford Foundation (Box 40)
    - Cooperative Program in Teacher Education (Box 40)
    - Duke Press Grant (Box 40)
    - Economics Grant (Box 40)
    - Fund for the Advancement of Education (Box 40)
    - International Legal Studies (Box 40)
    - Medical School Grant (Box 40)
    - Political-Economic Development Grant (Box 40)
    - Public Affairs Grant (Box 40)
  - Fulbright Scholarships (Box 41)
  - Fund for Peaceful Atomic Development (Box 41)
  - Fund for the Advancement of Education, [5 folders] (Box 41)
  - Fund for the Advancement of Education, [3 folders] (Box 42)
  - Correspondence (Box 42)
    - Ga-Gm (Box 42)
    - Gn-Gre (Box 42)
    - Grf-Gz (Box 42)
  - General Education Board (Box 42)
  - General Education Board (Box 43)
  - General Electric Social Studies Seminar (Box 43)
  - Gray, Gordon (Box 43)
  - Greenhill, Maurice H. (Box 43)
  - Gross, Paul Magnus, [5 folders] (Box 43)
  - Guilford College -- Guilford College, NC (Box 43)
  - Correspondence (Box 44)
    - Haa-Harp (Box 44)
    - Harq-Has (Box 44)
    - Hat-Heq (Box 44)
    - Her-Hn (Box 44)
    - Hoa-Hoo (Box 44)
    - Hop-Hou (Box 45)
    - Hou-Hz (Box 45)
  - Hanes, Pleasant Huber (Box 45)
  - Hardin, Charles M. (Box 45)
  - Hart, Hornell Norris (Box 45)
  - Harward, Stephen C. (Box 45)
  - Henricksen, Gerhard Chester (Box 45)
  - Herring, Herbert James (Box 45)
  - High Point College -- High Point, NC (Box 45)
  - Highland Hospital (Box 45)